Imagine that you're starting a new
project with a brand new team of people.
No one on the team has
worked together before,
so this will be a new experience for
everyone.
To better understand how your
team might develop over time,
let's discuss the psychologist Bruce
Tuckman's five stages of team development.
Forming, storming, norming,
performing and adjourning.
These stages of development illustrate
how teams grow from a disparate group
of people into a high functioning unit.
You might even recognize
the characteristics of each stage from
previous experiences working on a team.
Tuchman's first stage of team
development is the forming stage.
At this point everything feels shiny and
new.
Individuals on the team are just
getting to know on another, and
they're eager to make a good impression.
And typically they're excited for
the work to begin.
During this stage, you as a project
manager should clarify project goals,
roles, and context about the project.
People are seeking guidance and
it's your job to provide that guidance.
The second stage of team
development is the storming stage,
this is where things get a bit trickier.
As people settle into their roles and
the work on their project begins,
the people on your team are interacting
more and maybe disagreeing a bit.
This is where feelings of
frustration might emerge.
Individuals might take issues with certain
processes they feel are inefficient, or
other teammates they disagree with,
especially when the team is navigating
tasks that are much more complex
than they first appeared.
It makes sense, right?
If you're working closely with a new
group of people for the first time,
there's bound to be some
interpersonal conflict.
Teammates might disagree on time, and
effort estimations, vary in their
levels of independence, or
prefer to prioritize certain tasks
over other equally important tasks.
As the project manager, it's your
job to focus on conflict resolution.
Listen as the team addresses
problems to solve and
share insights on how the team
might better function as a unit.
After storming comes Tuchman's
third stage, the norming stage.
At this point,
the team has resolved some of its internal
conflict by establishing new norms.
Like processes and workflows that make it
easier for everyone to get things done.
The team feels better equipped to work
together efficiently and effectively.
You, as the project manager
should codify the team norms,
ensuring that the team is aware of those
norms and reinforce them when needed.
For example, if you've agreed to discuss
solutions to issues during weekly team
meetings, ensure that your weekly agenda
budgets time for this topic each week.
Tuchman's fourth stage
is the performing stage.
During this time, the team works together
relatively seamlessly to complete tasks,
reach milestones and
make progress toward the project goal.
In the performing stage,
you as the project manager should focus on
delegating, motivating and providing
feedback to keep up the team's momentum.
The fifth and final stage of team
development is the adjourning stage.
In this stage the project is wrapping up
and it's time for the team to disband.
It can be a bittersweet time for
the team and
you might want to mark the end of
the project with a celebration.
You as the project manager should set up
time to celebrate the final milestones and
success of the project as a group.
And be sure each member of your
team knows what's next for them.
Okay, to recap, Tuckman's five stages
of team development are forming,
storming, norming,
performing and adjourning.
These stages of team
development come together to
form a helpful framework you can use to
assess and recognize team dynamics, and
then adjust your management
style accordingly.
Team dynamics refer to the forces
both conscious and unconscious,
that impact team behavior and performance.
Managing team dynamics is a big part of
determining how to motivate your team.
It might be tempting to assume that people
can go full-speed ahead into a project.
But in reality,
it's important to take time to understand
the dynamics of your team overall and how
individual team members are fitting in.
This is especially important during
the more precarious forming and
storming stages.
Let's break down why managing
team dynamics is so important.
First, teams have individuals
with different skill sets,
varying degrees of autonomy,
and competing priorities.
It's your job to forge consensus and
set clear purposes, goals,
dependencies and accountability.
When teams function cohesively, they can
focus on the tasks and objectives at hand.
Another reason why it's important to
manage team dynamics is that it helps you
to create a collaborative and
psychologically safe environment.
When team members feel safe,
they're willing to help one another, and
accept help when they need it.
This benefits the entire project
by keeping schedules on track.
Though it can take time to
get to the performing stage,
using the norming stage as a time to
foster a collaborative environment can
help you get there quicker.
Understanding and
managing team dynamics can also help you
understand how to motivate your team.
Motivated team members are likely to
contribute more to discussions, complete
their tasks and actively participate
in other project activities.
A positive team atmosphere can
help employees feel empowered.
More comfortable taking calculated risks,
and
more likely to seek out innovative
solutions to complex problems.
Remember, so much of team dynamics
happens under the surface.
Identifying and understanding the stages
of team development can help you make
sense of how dynamics
are playing out on your team.
This can help you to be a better leader.
Coming up, we'll discuss what
it means to promote ethical and
inclusive leadership in the workplace.
Meet you there.